John DePol Collection
John DePol Collection
1935-1996
DePol, John, 1913-2004.
5 linear ft.
Biographical material, correspondence, exhibition materials, lecture and workshop materials, artwork, and equipment of renowned American wood engraver, John DePol.
150240
Biographical History
John DePol (1913-2004) was an American engraver, printer, book illustrator, and printmaker. Throughout his career, De Pol received several awards and honors, including the Richard Comyn Eames Museum Purchase Prize (1952) and the Kate W. Arms Memorial Prize (1955). In 1954, De Pol was appointed as an Associate of the National Academy of Design.
John DePol was born to Joseph and Theresa DePol on September 16, 1913, in Greenwich Village, New York. As the eldest of three children, DePol left high school early in order to support his family after his father’s untimely death. He began working as a statistical clerk and securities runner on Wall Street while attending night school where he learned typing and shorthand.
In March 1938, DePol enrolled at the Art Students League in Manhattan, taking evening classes in etching and lithography with instructor George Picken. Prior to this point, DePol was a self-taught artist, sketching Manhattan scenes and landmarks and printing etchings on his own hand-built intaglio press.
With the dawning of World War II, DePol served in the United States Army Air Force from 1943-1945. While on duty in Northern Ireland, he began taking classes at the College of Art in Belfast. During this period, DePol also sketched many of the sights and scenes in Ireland, England, and France, drawings that would later serve as the basis for many prints and book illustrations.
Upon returning to the United States, DePol began working as a production assistant at Lewis F. White Company, a small commercial printing firm. His experiences at L. F. White Company allow DePol to learn all about typography. After L. F. White Company, DePol worked in the private studio of Bernard Brussel-Smith, one of the finest wood engravers in America. During this time, DePol began doing independent work for private presses such as the Between-the-Hours Press of Ben Grauer, Prairies Press of Carroll Coleman, Zauberberg Press of Donn Drenner, and Hammer Creek Press of John Fass.
Throughout his career, DePol received several awards and honors, including the Richard Comyn Eames Museum Purchase Prize (1952) and the Kate W. Arms Memorial Prize (1955). In 1954, DePol was appointed as an Associate of the National Academy of Design.
Shortly after returning to the United States in 1945, DePol married Thelma Roth. They had one daughter, Patricia DePol. John DePol died on December 15, 2004 at the age of 91, near his home in Cliffside Park, N.J.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John DePol Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, subject files, artwork, and artist equipment. Biographical Material contains photographs of John DePol. Correspondence consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, as well as correspondence to and from others. Subject File contains exhibition materials, workshop and lecture materials, and information on other collections of John DePol's work. The collection also contains many examples of DePol's art works, as well as a selection of his wood blocks and printing tools, located in Artwork and Equipment respectively.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically and Subject File is arranged alphabetically. Artwork is organized into subject files and arranged alphabetically by title, or subject if the title is unknown. In instances where a folder title is italicized, the name given is the known title of the work or publication; otherwise, the name given is an assigned subject. Equipment, including wood blocks and printing tools, are located at the end of the collection.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Publishing, printing and book arts; DePol, John, 1913-2004.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790.; Marshall, John, 1755-1835.; Poe, Edgar Allan, 1809-1849.; Webster, Noah, 1758-1843.; Bacon, Francis, 1561-1626.; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321.; Baskerville, John, 1706-1775.; Dickens, Charles, 1812-1870.; Revere, Paul, 1735-1818.; Irving, Washington, 1783-1859.; Pickering Press.; Pentagram Press.; Yellow Barn Press.; Syracuse University.; Bucknell University.; Lycoming College.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Engravers -- United States.; Illustration of books -- United States -- 20th century.; Illustrators -- United States.; Printers -- United States.; Printmakers -- United States.; Wood engravers -- United States.; Wood engraving -- United States -- 20th century.; Limerick (Limerick, Ireland).; London (England).; Book illustrations.; Bookplates.; Broadsides (notices); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Wood blocks (printing blocks); Wood engravings.; Artists.; Engravers.; Illustrators.; Printers.; Printmakers.; Wood engravers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Portions of the Collection are a gift of John DePol.
Portions of the Collection are a gift of David Tatham.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General Correspondence (Box 1)
- Subject File
  - Exhibition Materials (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Materials (Oversize 1)
  - J. Johnson Co. (Box 1)
  - Lecture and Workshop Materials (Box 1)
  - Lecture and Workshop Materials (Oversize 1)
  - Other Collections of DePol's Works (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - About the Pier Where the Titanic was to Land (Box 1)
  - Ambidextrous (Box 1)
  - American Alumni Council News (Box 1)
  - American Artist, Mar. 1965 (Box 1)
  - An Anthology of Delaware Papermaking (Box 1)
  - Antiquarian Booksellers Association of America (Box 1)
  - Bacon, Francis (Box 1)
  - Ballylee, The Tower: Selections from the Tower Poems of W.B. Years, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Baskerville, John (Box 1)
  - Bomb Hit - Near Piccadilly, London 1944 (Box 1)
  - The Book Club of California Quarterly News-Letter, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Book Craftsmen Associates (Box 1)
  - A Boyhood in Iowa, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Broadsides (Oversize 1)
    At West Wills Long Island by William Heyen, Holiday Alter Trees by Dorothy Hobson Fitzgerald, Journey to the Interior by William Jay Smith, Why I Am Happy by William Stafford
  - Bucknell University (Box 1)
  - Bulmer, William (Box 1)
  - Buying Printing can be such Good Fun at the Pickering Press, print (Oversize 1)
  - California Flora (Box 1)
  - Carnes, A. Burton (Box 1)
  - Castle Press (Box 1)
  - Chipping Anger Aerodome, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 1)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 2)
  - Christopher Columbus: A Three Act Play by Charles Bertin, 1992 (Box 2)
  - The Church of Saint Luke in the Fields (Box 2)
  - Clarke & Way (Box 2)
  - The Club of Odd Volumes (Box 2)
  - Columbia University Press (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Gazette (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Gazette, four small prints on single large sheet (Oversize 1)
  - Country Derby (Box 2)
  - County Derry, Ireland, preliminary sketch in ink and pencil; presentation print for Print Club of Albany (Oversize 1)
  - The Curious Act of Poetry by Dorothy L. Hatch (Box 2)
  - Dante Alighieri (Box 2)
  - Dickens, Charles (Box 2)
  - Early Poems by Susan Perry, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Eliot-Sturgis-Prescott-Dreher House (Box 2)
  - Face to Face, "Twelve Contemporary American Artists interpret themselves in a limited edition of signed original wood engravings." (Oversize 1)
  - Faneuil Hall (Box 2)
  - Fass, John Stroble (Box 2)
  - Father Abraham by William Faulkner, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Four Stories by Alexander Pushkin, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Franklin Keepsakes (Box 2)
  - Franklin Keepsakes (Box 7)
  - From Dark to Light (Box 2)
  - Goudy, Frederic W. (Box 2)
  - Grauer, Ben (Box 2)
  - Harbour Island, the Bahamas (Box 2)
  - Harvard Medical School, Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine (Box 2)
  - Hudson's Bay Company (Box 2)
  - Irving, Washington (Box 2)
  - Juniata College (Box 2)
  - Lincoln's Journey to Greatness (Box 2)
  - Lycoming College (Box 2)
  - The Man Who Loved Islands by D.H. Lawrence, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Marshall, John (Box 2)
  - Mergenthaler Linotype Company (Box 2)
  - Modern Love by George Meredith (Box 2)
  - Monastery at Parey-Sous-Mont Fort, France (Box 2)
  - My Two Oxfords: An Essay by William Morris (Box 2)
  - Nypen News (Box 2)
  - Of Swinburne (Box 2)
  - Oil in Pennsylvania (Box 3)
  - Oscar Wilde: A Problem in Biography by Julian Symons, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Pentagram Press (Box 3)
  - Personal (Box 3)
  - Pickering Press (Box 3)
  - The Pit and the Pendulum by Edgar Allen Poe, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Poe, Edgar Allen (Box 3)
  - Print: The Magazine of the Graphic Arts (Box 3)
  - Printing History: The Journal of the American Printing History Association, 1987; 1989; 1990 (Box 3)
  - Printing Presses (Box 3)
  - The Quaker City Holy Land Excursion by Mark Twain (Box 3)
  - The Quill (Box 3)
  - Resurrection Ball (Box 3)
  - Revere, Paul (Box 3)
  - Saint Patrick (Box 3)
  - SAWE Journal (Box 3)
  - Self-Portrait, with Birds: Some Semi-ornithological Recollections by John Graves, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Sermon on the Mount (Box 3)
  - The Shore by William Heyen (Box 3)
  - A Show of Hands (Box 3)
  - Smith, Kline, & French Laboratory (Box 3)
  - Smith, William Jay (Poet) (Box 3)
  - Stanzas for an Imaginary Garden by Octavio Paz (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University (Box 3)
  - Syracuse University, Work done for John Mayfield (Box 3)
  - A Time for Recollection (Box 3)
  - Twain, Mark (Box 3)
  - Typophiles (Box 3)
  - University of Pennsylvania (Box 3)
  - We the Women (Box 3)
  - Webster, Noah (Box 4)
  - William Morris: Master Printer by Frank Colebrook (Box 4)
  - Williams College (Box 4)
  - Yale University Press (Box 4)
  - The Yalu Flows (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Oversize 1)
    American Antiquarian Society, Intersection, Iowa's Most Famous Barn, Legal Aide Society, The Meeting of the Waters of Hudson & Erie, Obed Gardner's Will, Phillips Exeter Academy Library, The Star Song: A Carroll to the King, Under Open Sky: Poets on William Cullen Bryant
  - Miscellaneous (Oversize 2)
    Beef; Bell and Flag Court, Lycoming; Bishops Gate, London; Bleeker Street; Bomb Hit, Near Piccadilly London 1944; Chapel in Belmont; Chimney Repair, Belfast; Clarke Memorial Chapel, Lycoming; Coal Hopper, North River; Drake Well in Titusville; Driftwood; Dusk, Belfast; Early Oil Refinery, Pennsylvania; Early Pipelines in Pennsylvania; Early Wells in Pennsylvania; Evening, Limerick; Factory District, Belfast; Ferry at Christopher St./Homeward Ferry; Fine Arts Building, Lycoming; Floating Crap Game; Hudson River Front; Illustration for The Trusting and the Maimed (Collection of Irish Short Stories by William Plunkett); Library, Lycoming College; Lonely Corner, Belfast; Mill on the Aspetuck; North River Front; Old Distillery at Ballyrowan; Old Flask (Success to the Railroad); Old Main, Lycoming College; Old Store Fronts, Limerick; Park Row, New York;; Quiet Afternoon in the Park; Railroad Bridge at Niantic; St. Mary's Gate, Limerick; Tower of Old Main, Lycoming; Twelfth Street, Manhattan; Ulster Railway Station
  - Miscellaneous, Sketches and print (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, Sketches and print (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, Reproductions (Box 4)
- Equipment
  - Wood Blocks (Box 5)
  - Wood Blocks (Box 6)
  - Tools, Assorted blocks and tools (Box 6)